本模块之前的视频是几年前录制的
so the prior videos in this module were recorded several years ago
正如Yan提到的
and as Yan mentioned
堆会经历
the heap kind of goes through
安全与效率的循环
cycles of emphasizing efficiency versus security versus efficiency
并不是说哪一个更重要
and it's not that one's more important than the other
而是有个权衡在里面
there's always a trade off
一方面追求高效率
going for something that's more efficient
另一方面则是安全性
versus going for something that's more secure
当添加一种安全机制
anytime that you add a mitigation technique
它让系统更安全
something to try and make a system more secure
但这是有代价的
there's always some kind of cost to it
无论是真实存在的资源消耗，亦或是人力消耗
whether it's a resource cost a real cost or a human cost
取舍一直都在
and so there's always trade offs there
至于更注重哪个
and as far as what the focus is
这要看哪个更流行了
that kind of depends on the flavor of the month
这取决于开发者的想法
it depends on what's on developer's minds
有哪些安全新闻
it depends on what's in the news right
就是看趋势
just kind of what's trend
最近，安全一直是一个热门话题
as of late security has been kind of a hot topic
所以当我们讨论堆的时候
and so when we talk about the heap
肯定有一些保护机制
there's definitely some mitigation techniques
在堆里的单链表中被实现
that are implemented in singly linked list heap implementations
比如tcache或Fastbin
like tcache or Fastbin
是值得讨论的
that are worth talking about
所以在这个视频中
and so in this video
我们将讨论一个已经出现的漏洞保护机制
we're going to talk about one of the kind of exploit prevention techniques that exists
这就是所谓的安全链接
and it's called safe linking
先来看安全链接要阻止什么
and so we're going to take a look at what safe linking attempts to prevent
然后看看保护机制是如何实现的
we're then going to look at how those prevention mechanisms are implemented
之后讨论它的有效性
and then we're going to discuss how effective these prevention mechanisms are
最后说说攻击者如何绕过它
and how a committed attacker can get around them
我们将从攻击者的角度分析它
so we're going to approach this from the attacker's viewpoint
对于攻击者来说，如果你在做堆漏洞利用
and for an attacker if you're doing a heap exploit
通常想要的
a very common thing that you'll want to try and do
或者说一个好目标，是堆上的指针
or Juicy Target is going to be a pointer on the heap
对于tcache来说，就是next
right like the for tcache it would be the next pointer
攻击者对next指针感兴趣有几个原因
and there's a couple of reasons that the next pointer is interesting to an attacker
首先，如果我能读取它
the first is if I can read it
如果我能读取这个值
if I can read that value
我可以消除一些随机性
I can eliminate some randomness
至少是堆基址的随机性
as far as ASLR on the heap
可以弄清随机的基址
I've eliminated the random bytes that exist in that space
如果我能读取next指针
if I can read that next pointer
我还获得了一些关于堆上内存布局的信息
I also gain some information about the layout of memory on the heap
我知道了另一个chunk的位置
so I now have some idea of where another chunk is located
对于高级的堆利用
and for an advanced heap exploit
它可能是成功利用的关键信息
that may be very critical information for me to pull off the exploit
现在
now
另外
alternatively
我可以试着覆盖next指针
I could try overwrite this next pointer
为什么我要覆盖next指针
and the reason I'd be interested in overwriting the next pointer
是因为当chunk被释放时
is because when the chunk is freed
不好意思，不是释放，是当被malloc后
I'm sorry not freed when the chunk is malloced
next指向的chunk将成为链表的新头节点
the next pointer becomes the next chunk
节点的编号都提前了一号（第2变第1，第3变第2）
everything moves up the list
如果设置正确的话
and so if set up correctly
调用几次malloc后
malloc is called a number of times
篡改的next值将被malloc返回
that next value can get returned by malloc
而且是被当作合法指针
as a valid pointer
这样后果很严重
and that's an extremely powerful thing to have
因为如果malloc被调用了
because if malloc is being called
调用malloc的程序
then the program that is calling malloc
一般会在这个地址上读或写
likely performs reads or writes on that pointer
毕竟不会无缘无故调用malloc
there's a reason that the program called malloc in the first place
所以覆盖next指针
and so by overwriting this next pointer
是实现任意读写的常见方法
it's a very common pathway to get an arbitrary read or an arbitrary write
如果我能控制next指针
if I can control this next pointer
然后让malloc返回它
and get malloc to return it
很大可能可以读写我想要的任意地址
there's a very high chance that I can read or write anywhere that I choose to in memory
现在
now
安全链接试图阻止它
safelinking attempts to prevent this
它通过加密空闲chunk中的next指针实现
and it does so by mangling and messing up that next pointer value in the free chunk
每个空闲chunk的next指针都会被异或
and so inside every free chunk that next pointer gets xord
它会和一个随机数异或
it gets xord with some random bytes
这样，攻击者在（读写）两个方面都陷入了困境
and so this kind of messes up the attacker on both fronts
如果我是攻击者
if I'm the attacker
我读取这个加密后的next值
and I'm reading this mangled next value
好吧
well
它被异或了，被打乱了
the value has been xord it's been messed up
我无法获取随机基址
so I don't learn anything about the ASLR bytes right
因为它已经被异或了
because those of those have been xord
堆内存空间也不明显了
and so it's not immediately obvious what does the memory space look like
因为它是一个被加密的指针
and because it's a mangled pointer that's been xord
无法通过它找到下一chunk在哪里
I also can't look at it and have any idea where the next chunk is located
没有得到任何关于堆布局的有用信息
I don't gain any information about the layout of heap memory that I could possibly manipulate
所以无法通过读取这个值获得任何信息
so I don't gain any information by viewing this value
如果我要覆盖它
now if I'm going to try and overwrite it
我是可以用我想要的值覆盖它
I could overwrite it and put my own value there
但我们会在后面几张幻灯片中看到
but as we'll see in a couple slides
因为加解密，它也不会生效
that will also not be very effective because of this mangling and demangling
所以
so
安全链接可以归结为两点
safe linking comes down to just two simple rules
第一个是会加密 tcache中空闲chunk的 next
the first we just saw which is the tcache next pointers must be mangled for free chunks
他会和一个随机数异或
so it's xord with some random bytes
这使得攻击者很难读取并获取信息
and that makes it difficult for the attacker to read and gain information
它也使攻击者覆盖它后
and it makes it difficult for the attacker to overwrite that
很难有一个成功的结果
and have a successful outcome
第二点是解密
the second rule is demangled pointers
加密后的值被存储在这里
so they're stored here in a mangled state
在特定的时候
but at some point
它需要解密回一个合法指针
that next value needs to get converted back to a valid pointer
这样malloc才能返回一个有效的指针
so that malloc can return a valid pointer
经过解密后
and after the demangling procedure
重点来了，指针的最低有效半字节必须是0
the rule is the pointer's least significant nibble must be 0
乍一看第二点的要求好像不严格
now this second rule doesn't seem like much
但它却对攻击者有很大影响
but it does have an impact to an attacker
首先，如果我用自己加密后的值覆盖它
the first is if I try and just write my own mangled messed up value
我走了大运才能成功
I have to get lucky
因为最低有效半字节
because the least significant nibble
必须和一个随机数异或
must xor with the random bytes
解密结果得是0
such that the least significant nibble is zero
这样自然大概率直接失败
and so that automatically makes it more likely that I'm going to just fail
因为失败几率更大
because the fail state is greater
另外
additionally
因为解密后指针（最低有位半字节）必须是0
because the demangled pointer must be 0
这就意味着
that means there are
大量的
a large number of
有效的内存地址
valid memory addresses
malloc都无法返回
that simply cannot be returned by malloc
比如一个完全有效的内存地址
like a totally valid memory address
在64位系统中，对齐的地址末尾是8
as far as like offset aligned on a 64 bit system is just something that ends in 8
使用的大多数合法地址都是8字节对齐的
most valid memory addresses that you're working with are 8 byte aligned
末尾不是0就8
so it's it's 0 or 8
好吧
well
如果你想从堆中获取一个指针
it turns out if you're going to get a pointer from the heap
末尾是8不行了
8 is no longer an option
对于攻击者来说，这意味着
and so for an attacker this means that
我可能对以8结尾的内存地址感兴趣
I may be interested in a memory location that ends in 8
但是我无法让堆返回我想要的指针
but I can't get the heap to return a pointer that is exactly what I want
这就增加了复杂性
and so this causes additional complexity
对于攻击者来说，这是一种额外的头痛
and kind of additional headache for an attacker
我们会发现
and so we'll see
这两个简单的规则
that these two simple rules
阻止了大量经典堆攻击
prevent a large number of just like classical heap attacks
并不能阻止所有
doesn't prevent all of them
堆攻击仍然可能发生
and the heap attacks that still can occur
它们还能用
they still work
但他们需要付出更多的努力才能实现
but they're going to require a bit more effort to pull off
因为我们必须考虑到这两条规则
because we have to account for these two rules
让我们回到攻击者的角度来思考
so let's go back to thinking like an attacker
我们来试一下利用
and we're going to try and pull off an exploit
我们会试着覆盖next指针
and so we're going to try and overwrite this next pointer
从之前Yan的视频可知
and from Yan's earlier videos we saw
最近释放的chunk位于列表的头部
that the most recently freed chunk is at the head of the list
头指针存储在tcache_per_thread结构体中
and the head pointer is stored in the tcache_per_thread struct
它有一个数组，每个元素有一个计数器和指针
and it has a list of counts and then a pointer
这个指针指向头节点或者说是对应bin的entry
to the head or to the first entry for that bin
作为攻击者
and so as an attacker
假设我得到了
we'll assume somehow I've obtained
指向这个空闲chunk的指针
a pointer to this freed chunk
我的策略是尝试覆盖next指针
and so my strategy is I'm going to try and overwrite this next pointer
因为我要控制它
because I want to control that
看看能否让malloc返回一个我需要的值
and see if I can get malloc to return a value I'm interested in
现在它的目标chunk是这里的chunk2
now the intended chunk is going to be chunk 2 over here
chunk2也有一个next指针
and chunk 2 has a next pointer as well right
但它不重要
but that doesn't matter
因为现在我们关注的是chunk1
because right now we're focused on chunk1
作为攻击者，我要覆盖这个next指针
and so as an attacker I'm going to overwrite this next pointer
完成后
and when I do that
这里是一个新的值
we now have a new next value there
现在什么都没发生
now nothing has really occurred right
我们只是把它覆盖了
we've just overwritten this
如果你做过这个模块的题目
now if you've done some of the problems in the module here
你肯定知道，在这种状态下
you've seen that in this type of a state
你可以调用malloc
you can call malloc
调用后
and when you do that
chunk1将被malloc返回
chunk 1 will get returned by malloc
然后修改后的next将被解引用
and then new next would get dereferenced
所以这个bin的head
and so the head of that bin
即下次malloc的返回值
the next entry to be returned by malloc
变成了新的next
becomes whatever was in new next
在本例中是Not_a_Chunk2
in this case it's Not_a_Chunk2
攻击者很可能不会
it's more than likely an attacker isn't going
用有效chunk覆盖next指针
to overwrite the next pointer with a valid chunk
他们会用一些
they're going to overwrite it with some
他们感兴趣的某个内存地址
it's just some address in memory that they're interested in
只要不崩溃
as long as the heap doesn't explode doesn't crash
攻击者不在乎
the attacker doesn't really care
只要在达成目标前程序不崩溃就行
it only needs to not break for long enough to accomplish what you need
这就是没有安全链接的情况
now this is what happens without safe linking
好的
right
新的next值被传递到tcache_per_thread结构体中
that new next value gets passed up into the tcache_per_thread struct
不管攻击者指定了什么
and whatever the attacker defined
下次malloc都会返回它
will be the next thing that's returned by malloc
但是有了安全链接后
however with safe linking
我们可以看到
what we see is that new next value
新next值加载到tcache_per_thread结构体之前
before it gets loaded up into the tcache_per_thread struct
它要经历一个解密的过程
it goes through a demangling phase right
因为我们必须通过XOR来解密
because we have to unxor it via XOR
它一个可逆的过程
because it's you know a reversible operation there
但这个过程仍会改变新的next
but still the demangling procedure is going to change the value of new next
结果不再是这样
so instead of looking at something like this
而是这样
the attacker ends up with something like this
bin的头将指向一个加密后的地址
and so the head entry of the bin will point to some mangled address
它很可能是一个无效的内存地址
more than likely it will be an invalid memory address
这甚至是不可解引用的
that isn't even dereferenceable
另外，因为我们有这个规则
additionally because we have that rule
最低有效半字节必须是0
that the least significant nibble must be zero
很可能
there is a very good chance
这个地址都没对齐（末尾不是0）
that this address will not even be properly aligned
这意味着它会导致
which means that it can result in
堆因为对齐问题终止程序
the heap causing the whole program to just stop because of an alignment issue
这对攻击者来说是个问题
and so this is a problem for the attacker
虽然这让攻击者很头疼
now despite being quite the headache for the attacker
但安全链接的实现出奇地简单
the implementation of safe linking is surprisingly simple
其实就是这三行C宏
it is really just these three lines which are just C macros
我们来看一下
so let's take a look at them here
有一个PROTECT_PTR，它接受一个pos和一个ptr
we have PROTECT_PTR which takes a position and a pointer
pos被 >> 12位
the position value is bit shifted to the right by 12
那么这12位的意义是什么呢
bits so what's the significance of this 12 bits
如果你回忆一下内存模块
well if you recall from the memory module
我们学了ASLR
we encountered something called ASLR
它在课程和业界都存在一段时间了
it's been around now for a while in the modules and out in the world
内存地址的前3个半字节用作内存页中的偏移
but the first three nibbles of a memory address are offsets into a page we said
这3个半字节是固定的
and so those tend to be pretty consistent
剩下的是随机基址
after that are random byte values
每次程序运行时生成的都是不同的
that are generated that are different every time the program runs
由于地址空间布局随机化
due to address Space Layout Randomization ASLR
所以当我们位移了12位
and so when we bit shift by 12 bits
我们做的是
what we're doing is
只保留ASLR产生的随机基址
we are moving those random bits or those random bytes from ASLR
存储在pos中（去掉了地址中的固定偏移量）
up to the front of this position value
我们要用这个随机数和ptr异或
because we want these random bytes to be xord into the pointer
这是这行代码的意思
and that's what we see here
只在pos中保留随机基址
so we move the randomness to the front of position
然后用ptr与他异或
we then xor with the pointer
这就得到了一个加密值
and that gives us a mangle value
现在我们来看一下REVEAL_PTR的实现
now if we look at the implementation of REVEAL_PTR
REVEAL_PTR是用PROTECT_PTR实现的
REVEAL_PTR is defined as PROTECT_PTR
它是PROTECT_PTR，参数是ptr地址以及ptr
it's PROTECT_PTR with the address of a pointer with the pointer's value
这两个宏都只是可逆的异或操作
and so in both cases it's just a reversible xor
所以
so
让我们从攻击者的角度来考虑这个问题
let's think about this from the attacker standpoint
哪里使用了这两个函数
well where are these functions used
又是在哪里实现的
where are these macros implemented
如果我们看一下这里
well if we take a look here
REVEAL_PTR在malloc中
REVEAL_PTR is inside malloc
具体来说，它在tcache_get中
specifically it's inside tcache_get
因为malloc要返回指针
because malloc returns pointers
它需要从tcache中获取chunk
so that is getting something from the tcache
把它返回给malloc调用者
and returning it to whoever called malloc
如果我们看一下这段代码
and if we look at this snippet here or this block of code
我们首先看到的是
the first thing we see is
从bin的头节点获取了 tcache_entry e
the tcache entry e is pulled from the head of the bin
tcache->entries[tc_idx]
so tcache Entries index
从tcache_per_thread结构体中获取对应bin的头节点
that is grabbing the head entry for the correct bin from the tcache_per_thread struct
拿到了bin中的第一个节点
so it's getting the first entry
然后检查地址是否对齐
it then checks that entry to see if it's aligned
就在这里检查了最低有效半字节是否为0
this right here is where that does the least significant nibble equal 0 check as occurring
即，地址是否对齐
we're saying is is this entry aligned
如果没有对齐，我们看到malloc打印错误
if it's not aligned we see malloc print err
检测到未对齐的tcache chunk
unaligned tcache chunk detected
然后完了
and then the heap is done
程序将退出
the program will exit
接下来我们看这儿
next we see here
我们最初关注的REVEAL_PTR
this REVEAL_PTR which is what we initially were kind of focused on
现在调用了REVEAL_PTR(e->next)
now REVEAL_PTR is being called on e->next
就是首个chunk的next
so that's going to be the head's next pointer
它被解密。然后
and that's going to get demangled and
存储在tcache_per_thread结构体的head
stored in the head entry of the tcache_per_thread struct
因此，在tcache_per_thread结构体中是被解密的指针
so inside the tcache_per_thread struct are demangled pointers
但是tcache_per_thread结构体之外的
but everything outside of the tcache_per_thread struct
都被加密了
is a mangled pointer
然后减少计数
we then decrement the count
因为空闲的chunk被从bin中选中用于重利用
because remallocing and returning from the bins
然后返回一个正常对齐的地址
and we return the entry that we know is properly aligned
那么释放时发生了什么
now what happens inside a free
非常相似
well very similar
只不过这里变成了PROTECT_PTR
except this is where the PROTECT_PTR operation occurs
就在这里加密
so this is where we are going to mangle something
然后把它放到tcache缓存列表中
and then push it onto the tcache list
这里是tcache_put
and so here we have tcache_put
因为我们又在列表中添加了一个entry
because again we are putting an entry onto the list
所以我们要把一个chunk转换成一个entry
and so we're going to convert a chunk to an entry
我们要设置key
we're going to set the key value which
Yan在之前讲了key是什么
Yan described what the key is in earlier modules
是一个指向tcache_per_thread结构体的指针
should just be a pointer to the tcache_per_thread struct
然后我们看到PROTECT_PTR被调用
we then see PROTECT_PTR is called
参数是next的地址
and PROTECT_PTR is called on the address of next
还有tcache中的head
with the tcache head entry
它的返回值放到e->next中
and that is what gets stored in e->next
然后用e->next的地址
so we're going to take the address of e->next
和head
with the thing that was at the head
异或
xor them together
加密结果存储在e->next中
and that is the mangled value that will get stored in e->next
作为加密后的next指针
as the mangled next pointer
这就是安全链接的原理
and so that is how safe linking works
还有几处调用
there are other calls
如果查看源代码
if you want to see the source code
在堆中还有其他地方
there are other places
使用了PROTECT_PTR和REVEAL_PTR
where PROTECT_PTR and REVEAL_PTR are used in the heap in general
但就tcache而言
but as far as tcache goes
这是你应该关注的两个关键领域
these are the two key areas that you should focus on
我们已经看到了这些宏在哪里被使用
so we've seen where these macros are used
但是该如何理解它呢
but what do we know about the actual implementation here
我们说这很简单
we said it's really simple
好像我们作为攻击者总能做点什么
like there's got to be something we can do as an attacker
所以让我们仔细看看
so let's take a closer look
这里的宏或者函数
at the actual macros or the actual functions that are occurring here
我们知道异或是可逆的
so we know XOR is reversible
我们来看看这个PROTECT_PTR
so let's look at this PROTECT_PTR
它是用pos和ptr异或
well we said that it's xoring this position value with the pointer
我不知道pos的值
but I don't necessarily know the position value
所以这里需要两个不同的值
so I need two different values here
要知道这个pos
I need to have this position
还要知道这个ptr
and I need to have the pointer
PROTECT_PTR
and so PROTECT_PTR
至少从这里看是这样的
at least by looking at it here initially
如果没有这两个值就无法解密
it cannot be reversed without two values
所以我需要这两个值
so I need to have both of these things
来用xor解密
in order to try and reason about how I'm going to xor
那REVEAL_PTR是如何实现的呢？
what about REVEAL_PTR
至于REVEAL_PTR
well REVEAL_PTR
如果您还记得的话，它是由PROTECT_PTR定义的
if you'll recall is defined by PROTECT_PTR
所以我们可以将这里的参数
and so we can substitute in the arguments here
就是ptr的地址
which is the address of pointer
和ptr的值
with the value of pointer
代入到PROTECT_PTR
into PROTECT_PTR
我们最后得到了什么呢
and so what do we end up with
我们得到的结果是这样的
we end up with something that looks like this
REVEAL_PTR将
so REVEAL_PTR is going to
ptr的值和ptr地址的基址异或
xor the pointer value with the address of the pointer bit shifted by 12 bits
那么
now
如果这里使用的ptr
if the pointers that were used here
是随机分布在内存里的
were randomly located in memory
这将是一个难题
this would be a difficult problem
但
but
所有这些都发生在堆中
all of this is occurring in the heap
也就是说
which means that
我们把这12位页内偏移去除掉后
and we're bit shifting away the offset into the page these 12 bits
ptr地址去除12位偏移量后
so the more than likely the address of pointer bitshifted 12
会等于
is going to be equivalent to
ptr的值（去除12位偏移量）
the pointer itself
前提是ptr指向堆地址
assuming that the pointer points to the heap
所以
it's going to be
ptr的值右移12位
the pointer bit shifted 12
基本等同于
is going to be roughly equivalent like most of the time
ptr的地址右移12位
to the address of the pointer bit shifted by 12
这点是
and this knowledge is key
理解REVEAL_PTR函数
to realizing that this REVEAL_PTR function
能仅凭密文逆推明文的关键
is fully reversible from the mangled value alone
我就不教你怎么做了
now I'm not going to show you how to do it
我相信你能查找到
I'm sure you can look it up
但是如果你使用ipython尝试一下
but if you play around with just ipython like in a terminal here
研究研究
and look at this and think about it
你能想清楚这个的
you'll figure out how you can reverse this
所以你可以取一个加密后的值
so you can take one value that mangled value
然后返回一个合法的堆地址
and get back a valid heap pointer
这有一些含义
now this has some implications
如果我们能破解REVEAL_PTR
so if we can reverse this REVEAL_PTR function
之前说，如果没有那两个值，就无法破解PROTECT_PTR
well we said PROTECT_PTR cannot be reversed without two values
其中一个是pos值
but one of those values that we needed was this position value
而这个pos值就是一个有效的堆指针
and this position value is a valid heap pointer
所以如果能破解REVEAL_PTR来获得一个有效的堆地址
so if I can reverse REVEAL_PTR to get a valid heap pointer
就可以在PROTECT_PTR中使用这个堆地址
then I can use that valid heap pointer in PROTECT_PTR
然后破解PROTECT_PTR
to then reverse the value of PROTECT_PTR
所以你可以
and so you can
当你得到一个加密后的指针
once you get a mangled pointer value
可以将它恢复成正常堆地址
turn that into a valid pointer value or heap pointer value
然后使用那个有效的堆地址
and then use that valid heap pointer value
然后在将它写入空闲chunk的next指针前重新加密
to then remangle things before you write them into freed chunk's next pointers
只要收集足够的信息，就可以自己加密
so you can do the mangle in yourself once you collect enough information here
这样你不再写入明文值
so that you don't write a clear text value
自己加密，然后写入密文
you mangle it yourself and write a mangle value
因为你知道堆是如何处理它的
because you understand and know how the heap is going to demangle it
这一切都需要一个泄露漏洞
and all this requires is one leak
比以前多需要了一个泄露漏洞
it's still one more leak than you used to have to have
因为你以前根本不需要泄露信息
because you used to not have to have the leak at all
所以必须找到一个堆泄露
and so you do have to get a heap leak
在开始自己加解密前
before you can begin this kind of mangling and demangling yourself
之后才能进行更复杂的堆利用
and when you start doing more complicated heap exploits
堆利用可能涉及多个分配
where there may be multiple allocations
涉及到许多指针，这些指针可能在堆上，也可能不在堆上
involved in many pointers that may or may not be on the heap
它变得更加复杂
it becomes a lot more complicated
只是为了写入东西到next中
just to get something that is passable into the next pointer
当有堆泄露时，这实际上并不难
it's actually not that hard once you have an initial heap leak
所以关于安全链接的要点是
so the takeaways here in thinking about safe linking right
它确实为大多数堆利用增加了额外的要求
it does add additional requirements to most heap exploits
大多数时候，您都试图与空闲chunk中的元数据进行交互
most of the time you're trying to interact with the metadata that is in free chunks
next指针是主要目标，原因有很多
and the next pointer is a prime target for a lot of reasons
这个对齐检查
these alignment checks
确保了最低有效半字节是0
making sure that the least significant nibble is zero
直接防止
directly prevents each
即使你能自行加解密
even when you can do this demangling and mangling
能自己加解密也没用
it doesn't matter if I can do the mangling and demangling
仍然有一些地址你无法让堆返回
there are still addresses that you cannot get the heap to return to you
作为攻击者，你要做的就是
and so as an attacker what you'll try and do is
返回在它之前，或者之后的地址
return something that is just preceding it or just after it
这取决于上下文
depending upon the context
也许我可以返回一个在目标地址之前的地址
maybe I can return a pointer that comes before what I'm interested in
然后我要做一些填充
and then I have to do some padding
来将要写入的东西打印出来
to get something to print out I have to write
我可能拿到目标地址前8字节的地址
I can get something that's 8 bytes before the thing I'm interested in that I want to read
所以我要先填冲上8个a
so then I have to pad 8 as
然后调用put 输出字符串
and then call like put string right
所以你需要在
and so you have to get a bit more creative in how you're going to try and
利用malloc返回指针这方面，更有创造力
utilize the pointers that are returned by malloc
这就导致了额外的麻烦和复杂性
and so that this leads to additional like keep ups and complications
在你写漏洞利用的时候
when you're trying to write your exploits
正如我提到的
as I mentioned
因为这个加解密流程
because of this mangling and demangling
尽管这是可逆的
even though it is reversible
要破解它，你必须
to be able to reverse it you have to have
有一个堆指针泄漏漏洞
a heap pointer leak
可以是一个加密后的堆指针
it can be a mangled heap pointer to be clear
但最终因为你能将密文解密成合法指针
but ultimately because you can turn a mangled heap pointer into a valid heap pointer
只需要利用密文指针中的信息
just with the information contained in the mangled pointer
在这种情况下，密文指针是完全有效的
so a mangled pointer is totally valid in this case
我只是想确认一下我讲清楚了
I just want to make sure I'm clear about that
当得到一个密文的堆指针
so getting a mangled heap pointer
您可以将其转换为有效的堆指针
you can turn that into a valid heap pointer
而一旦你知道了堆指针
and once you have that heap pointer leak
你可以自己加密堆指针
you can begin to mangle things yourself
但是，在获得有效的堆指针之前，您无法自行加密
you can't mangle things until you get a valid heap pointer though
所有这些我提到的
and all of this as I mentioned
增加了复杂堆利用的复杂性
leads to a lot more complications trying to do complex heap exploits
比如堆按摩
like massaging the heap
创建重叠的分配
you're creating overlapping allocations or
得到重叠的分配，这样你就可以
getting overlapping allocations so that you can then
覆盖指针，然后任意读
overwrite a pointer to then get a read
或者将栈地址放到堆中
or you're trying to for instance put a stack value somewhere in the heap
或者将libc地址放到堆中
or a Lib C value somewhere in the heap
突然之间
well all of a sudden
之前的一些假设
some of these assumptions that existed
比如这个
like this one here
它完全可逆的
about this being fully reversible
因为ptr地址和ptr值在同一个内存区域
because the address of the pointer should be in the same memory region as the pointer itself
不一定是对的了
is not necessarily true
因为突然之间，你能输入不同内存区域的地址
because all of a sudden you're putting values from different memory regions
让他们异或
together in xoring them
这肯定会引起一些问题
and that can definitely cause some issues
对于尝试做更复杂利用的攻击者来说
for an attacker trying to do a more complicated exploit
因为你必须非常清楚
because you have to be very aware
什么值在与什么值异或，才能正确的加密
of what value is getting xord with the other value to mangle it correctly
不让安全链接报错
such that safe linking doesn't break
所以这是一种有效的威慑
and so it is an effective deterrent
这是一种很好的保护机制
it is a good mitigation technique
对，这会增加攻击者的工作量
right it causes more work for the attacker
但它肯定不是万灵药
but it certainly isn't a cure-all
对于了解这种机制如何工作的攻击者来说
and for an attacker that is knowledgeable about how this mechanism works
他们花时间去获取需要的信息
and they put in the time to obtain the correct information
比如堆指针泄漏
like getting a heap pointer leak
它当然可以被一个有决心的攻击者所克服
it certainly can be overcome by a determined attacker
这些就是我要说的安全链接
so that's what I have to say about safe linking
这里有一些新的挑战被添加到dojo中
there are some new challenges that are being added to the dojo here
要用到安全链接
that will be using safe linking
你将看到安全链接如何改变和影响堆利用
so you'll get to see how safe linking changes and impacts how heap exploitation works